start mid-sentence hello welcome to the
idea cafe today we're talking about the
fifth and final issue of the questions
the whole point is they're never
answered we're done
we've reached enlightenment after this
week what am i ready to let go of is the
fifth and final question the burn part
of it
what is ready to be released in the
other four questions which are who am i
for my people what is my purpose and
what do I need and so you don't
necessary have to answer within that
context but that is how I generally look
at it like what am I willing to let go
of in those areas interests in general
whatever comes up I had I was thinking
about this this morning had look what am
I ready to let go of I don't know yeah
do you want to start we don't meet you I
can go first it's really interesting
because I was part of the reason why I'm
sometimes late is because I have a call
right before this and so we try and end
a few minutes early but we really like
talking to each other and so sometimes
we'll get wrapped up in something and
I'll take it right out up to the time
and and so in that context you know it's
like you know that question of Who am I
and what am i ready to let go of I have
a tendency to be strongly identified
with being someone who is intelligent
and as a result I am in a situation
where I don't feel like I am intelligent
or I somehow feel like I'm I used the
word I used the word simpleton last
night like I feel incredibly
uncomfortable and so I guess part of
what I'm ready to let go of is that my
identification with that intelligent
part of me and that somehow that
intelligence is a determination of my
worth as a person and what else am I
willing to let go of
the other thing that was coming up in
the conversation I was just having was
what kind of the embarrassment I feel at
being the embarrassment I feel at like
if someone I know has a hold the belief
that some people like it's like I have
this tendency to look at people I care
about through the lens of other people
that I know and you know that that sort
of guilty by association and so letting
go you know I want to continue to let go
of not caring about what other people
think because as a human I'm designed to
care about what other people think like
that's normal but to let go of that fear
of being rejected if I don't fit in yes
if so you know if somebody dislikes me
because of somebody I'm associated with
then that would be then that's the fear
of being rejected I think is that is the
thing that I'm that I'm more afraid of
than what people actually think and so
being willing to let go of that fear
yeah I don't know far
thank Simon John wrote you myself and
with only two of us I didn't even eat
myself mine's very similar when I'm
ready to let go of I've written here
what you said is that like intelligence
doesn't equal my worth um I've had to
deal with that so I don't see
intelligence is equally my worth anymore
but I still get into that mode sometimes
when I'm ready to let go of his stuff
that was coming up this week it's like
not speaking my truth because it might
hurt someone's feelings and not like me
not needing to not offend and not hurt
people which keeps me from from being
fully who I am and saying what I'm here
to say which then stops everything from
going because I said something that was
misconstrued and me and the person dealt
with
it was actually really great vigor I if
I hadn't said the thing which is
normally what I would have done so like
giving up what it is that then I can
possibly think of all the different
layers that could hurt someone because
when I was even doing that it still hurt
someone and letting go that that's my
responsibility at all letting go that
there's a right way to do in the first
place what is right kind of emerges and
it's about dealing with I can't go back
and change it anyway so why not you know
continue moving forward and looking at
repairing it and looking at with what
can we learn from this having happened
and this other thing that kept like
sitting with me weirdly this week is
this this is posted to boarding
broadcasts on it was like the shopping
cart catalyst or litmus test for whether
or not you're a good human being is
whether or not you returned a shopping
cart and I'm sure it wasn't either
you're good humans whether you could
handle self-governance because it's not
something that's illegal it's just like
you do it if you're doing the right
thing and there's no reason to not do it
and there's so much wrong with that that
I've just been sitting with me but I was
like no my version of self-governance is
you return the shopping cart if you
think it's the right thing to do and
assume goodwill in those who haven't and
it really bothers you the shopping carts
all over the place then do it if it's so
easy right like just clean him up and
move them back but anyway I had to tell
that story to say that like the irony
and all of that what I was unlike
self-governing is basically governing
yourself but in me like I'm trying to
self-govern what other people's version
of self-governance is right because
there's a layer thereof we can't control
each other we can only do ourselves and
the problem with the shopping cart is
that it and it triggers the person right
it's that it's like there and it annoys
you it's not the actual shopping cart
although there are problems with that as
well and so letting go of things needing
to be my way even if I can like fully
logically heart-space
everything see that it's the right way
it's like the irony of of like needing
people's version of self-governance to
include the diversity of the individual
while not allowing them to have the
diversity of the individual you don't I
mean that's their self-governance and so
I don't know letting go that the
universe makes sense in the most in like
the most beautiful way like right it's
gonna keep being sarcastically ironic
and I love it and I'm gonna let go I'm
trying to make sense of it a little
course about and continually make sense
of it but letting go of like that
rigidity of like holding to that sense
because it's kind of fun to think about
the self-governed about their self
governing it's like yeah but that's what
we need to do it if you fix the world so
it's just beep in that space is what I'm
like another sorry to write that what
that made me think of is you know
letting go or maybe more more precisely
being willing to let go of the story of
what other people's behavior means
because the thing that annoys you know
like when when I get annoyed with
somebody else it's the story it's the
projection I have about what their
behavior means and like I'm not always
willing to let go because sometimes I
want to hold on to my self-righteous you
know feelings of indignation like cuz
sometimes that's a warm blanket that
like feels good and I just want to hold
onto it and you know but but yeah having
you know you know there coz that what am
i ready to go let go of and what am i I
would add another question to that or a
like a slight variation which is what am
i ready to be willing to let go of like
I'm not I'm not I'm not ready to let it
go
but I'm I'm ready to be willing to let
it go like that's because sometimes all
I can do is be willing to let go you
know it's like you always be willing to
let go and maybe that's implied within
the question but you know so so
willing to let go of my my internal
model of someone else that is causing me
to you know judge them or make them
wrong for their actions
I'm sorry for my tardiness thank you you
normally are here before before we
started I was playing chess a lot second
time it happened like how its chassis
were playing them yeah I just got into
it there's this toy this is an
interruption but is this girl on YouTube
who's doing these analyses of alpha
zeros games and it's really interesting
is this computer plate just it's never
been taught how to play right so it
doesn't have all of the standard
openings in its files and all of that
kind of doesn't it's not burdened with
any of that it's just been told the
rules and the objectives and it's
figured it out itself and it plays
completely differently right just values
things completely different it's really
realized my interest in the game so I've
started playing again I was gonna say
like ready to let go of and whatnot
actually like all this this is in no way
a slight ahead you're like who needs a
clock like who needs to show up to
things like what is it this
I kind of wonder what society would look
like in that regard like we're having a
party at some point we're happy that's
at some point my understanding is that
that's actually very like much how
Middle Eastern society works like they
don't adhere they don't pay attention to
clocks like if you're if you go up like
that
people who are doing business with
people who are like especially in Saudi
Arabia I think that if you're if you go
there like be prepared that something
that starts at 2:00 like that's just a
suggestion of what time it might start
and like I have no I've never been able
to verify that but that would be really
interesting like what would it be if
everyone you know if everyone like
nobody really paid attention to clocks
like so this pretty
recent Kira it's really recent it's like
150 years that's all it is this
obsession with what time it isn't being
on time stuff it's it's only since
trains started running is only since we
need the timetables for trains that's
that's when it all stirred at everyone
was like it now is in Saudi Arabia it
was always like that would you think
about like the faster it gets the more
it's like that right the more first all
our coordinating time zones and you know
what I mean and so we kind of need to
know this start expand otherwise we have
like the game be coffee shop of great
and idea but there's no in there's you
don't have you know stuff to do we're
all so busy doing so know exactly like
any waiting around for four hours for a
thing to start right and therefore like
time becomes money and then it does
become like three minutes yeah I don't
know do you want to share the what do
you what what am I prepared to let go of
kind of thing all right something like
the one you yeah yeah it's funny I find
this the hardest one because I mean I've
I've let go of a lot but over the last
few but then it's been not hard for me
to do so right and so how much of a
lesson go is it if it's not actually
hard to do right I mean I think it needs
to be needs to feel like a sacrifice
otherwise you don't actually letting go
of anything right you're not attached to
it in the first place and they're
probably not letting go but really do
you know what I mean so yeah I've always
I've always struggled out of it a little
bit and so I wonder if I'm you know
withholding things that I that I am very
loath to let go of but I'm unaware of
doing that you know what I mean I think
I I wonder about that sometimes because
letting go of the job and letting go of
the house and letting go of the daily
routine and and and and you know taking
up a much different kind of that was all
quite easy for me despite the fact that
family and friends didn't really get it
what are you doing you're rushing into
things give it you know give it some
thought take some pirate blah blah blah
blah blah
I found all that quite easy but then I
don't have entanglements of kids
long-term relation fit you know serious
like my own business anything like that
nav any of those kinds of entanglements
so that makes it somewhat easier so yeah
I mean I don't know that the best
example I can think of of something that
I do not let go of that I would kind of
like to although is smoking right there
especially tobacco especially and that's
something I struggle to let go of I have
done on occasion in my life but I
struggled to do so significant long-term
so yeah that's kind of where I am on it
I you know it seems to me I I can give
up the big stuff easily with the small
stuff sort of peoples and things around
I wonder how much of this because it's
just like the first time I'm answering
these questions with people right how
much we can also like invite each other
to eat let things go right because when
you were talking Eric what came up for
me was can I invite you to let go that
it has to be a struggle to let something
go write it up they can be easy and fun
like I know one of the things I'm
willing to let go of but not yet ready
to let go of is my parent marijuana
right so it's like okay to Lou nuria me
like putting those things on it but it's
like it's too hard right now there's a
there's like all this stuff I know I'm
not capable completely yet I'm willing
to be ready
and that was what Kyra was mentioned was
this difference in the question between
what am i ready to let go over what am i
Williams like both and I think it is
like in there of that the beginning part
that ain't clean that like I'm willing
to want to let go of this technology and
that it's hard and then when is wit for
me anyway I know it's only ready to be
letting go of when it actually is easy
but it feels that shitty and a lot of it
is the outside world tell you no no no
no no no don't do that
right don't buy the farm that's not take
some time think about it but your
internal stuff then kind of clicks right
it becomes somewhat easier because
you're like that push back instead of
making afraid my life anyone's it making
me second-guess it makes me stand firmer
in it and then that's how I know that
it's like my thing to do that is
different than just doing it because
they say to or not doing it cuz they say
not to like that willingness to make
other
I guess is what I had talked about
during my letting people go are letting
it go it's like the need to fix
everything saving the world's on me I'm
willing not yet ready with a little wet
bag of the I had the same reaction in
Jubilee of Eric's that the idea that it
has to be something that that it has to
be painful it has to be something that
is you know it it can be like one of my
teachers she talks about how you know it
depends on on on how you want to learn
the lesson like if you want it to be
hard it can be hard if that is or if
that's what you need because for some
people that's what they need but it's
but it also doesn't have to be hard and
yeah I guess I guess the point I was
making that if it's not hard then
there's no actual letting go it's just
kind of slipped away on it stoned you
see what I mean that's that I guess
that's the point I was making and so
great I do understand you're saying and
I do have in my head the assumption
somewhere that letting go of stuff is
hard I do have that in me somewhere so
no it's good you've highlighted it well
in the next question that I would ask no
Eric would be how long have you been
thinking about doing that before you get
it oh not really very long at all I mean
I did rush into it but I was sure I
wanted to do it so great sometimes you
know sometimes it's like things line up
and all of a sudden it's like oh yeah
this this thing makes perfect sense so
you know it's sorry you know moving
towards grabbing hold of something new
rather than a letting go of anything
yeah and I guess that's I mean comes
back comes down to you the crux of like
one of the ideas behind game B is like
you know instead of destroying what you
don't want or tearing down what you
don't want building something better
and so it's like if you're moving to you
know if you're moving towards something
you know that that's you know it's like
that's a big question is am i we're
moving in the direction of something
that I want or am i moving away from
something I don't want because no right
but yeah because moving away from
something I don't want then there's
probably something that I haven't dealt
with yet you know that I need to deal
with and so yeah I think you know to me
that the crux of so much of why we end
up or white at least in the United
States like 50% of marriages end in
divorce and is because it's like people
move you know it's like well I don't
want this well what is it that you don't
want do you do not want the
uncomfortable feelings that are coming
to the surface now granted there are
certain situations where it makes
perfect sense but if you're not if
you're moving away from something versus
towards something you know there's very
different lessons yeah that that's that
the 50% of marriages end in divorce
contains within it an implicit
assumption that that's a bad thing right
that all marriages should last forever
and that that's a presupposition with
which I disagree right the you know this
this this idea of two people staying
together for 30 40 50 years to the
exclusion of all others i I don't see
that that necessarily you know like that
that seems to me to be very much of
quite recently there's a specific
analogy that is like if you're in a for
a marriage is kind of a contract to stay
together forever I mean I think in every
society that's what it's supposed to be
here and yet there comes a point where
the pain outweighs what you're getting
from it and so the quote for some people
the right thing to do is to stay in and
work through it and for some people the
right thing is to is to move on how do
you know both of those things are
letting go both of those things are like
letting go that the relationships
supposed to look like it's supposed to
be this marriage I had a 90 in my head
we're gonna work through this we're
gonna stay that's letting go of what
it's going to be versus letting go or
the relationship this is never going to
be where
can find it so hopefully someone
acknowledging that you're gonna find
those feelings everywhere but how much
is on this person there's something
there yeah anyway and I think you know
at least in the United States there's a
there's a marriage is not like yes I
agree with you Eric that marriage is you
know not every marriage is supposed to
last 30 40 whatever years maybe not
everyone's supposed to get married
that's all so the expectation is that
you get married right I mean everybody
gets married well maybe maybe that's a
flawed assumption also maybe there's I
like Jordan Peterson's framing on this
of like you are shackling yourself to
another human being and saying for good
or bad I you know we're gonna we're
gonna work through this and not to say
that there aren't some circumstances but
there is a level of uncovering of who
you are that is necessary to you know
it's like a will a willingness to let go
of your ideas of who you're supposed to
be who they're supposed to be what a
marriage is supposed to look like you
know my my marriage has done you know a
bazillion you know a complete 180 from
where what I thought marriage was
supposed to look like and I think
there's a lot of people who you know
aren't necessarily willing to let go of
their idea of who their partner is
supposed to be or who they are supposed
to be or what marriage is supposed to
look like that you know I I'm all for
the concept of open marriages and
polyamory and do your exploring but
there's something to be said for like
there being one person for to which you
are like you're you're you're shackled
with them you know you're shackled with
them and it being difficult and it's
difficult and painful to set to break
that
to break that again I know I do get that
and you need the commitment to hold you
together when it you should be staying
together because it's hard for now but
you know what I mean it's worth yeah I
do I do understand that I just I don't
know
no I you're going it's weird because
part of it is the transparency of
marriage part of it is that it is this
contract it's supposed to be forever and
that has somewhat outlived its
usefulness completely like we don't look
at work like that anymore right even if
you think you're going to the university
to have a career you're gonna be there
for 40 years we can see that's not the
case and we don't you know I mean we
don't look at you as broken because you
want to you know go back to university
and did something new and outgrew your
you know profession or the profession
changed and at the same time marriage is
like a business contract between two
people two families and then it became
more about love and and now we're like
working through our stuff together and
so like the idea when you're young in
the LA or whatever young love whether
you're Lera or not that we're gonna live
together like forever you're my soul
mate we're never is always naive always
there's always gonna be conflict but
there's also like I like the idea of
marriages needing to be renewed every
five to 10 years like what we're doing
is committing to five years of being
together and focusing right like and if
you break it beforehand it's broken but
at the same time it's like do we
recommit now to the next five years the
next five years and maybe kids takes a
minimum ten-year commitment right he's
like all right there this old at that
point but um I mean I'm not actually
advocating this but like the the
flipside of what is marriage in society
and can we change that right there's
common law there's all these other
things that aren't marriage marriage but
at the same time how much is society's
version of what America should be what I
should then take on if I already took it
on right well we're together forever
because that's what marriage is and then
I'm 20 years in and I'm like wait a
minute
this isn't what I like this isn't
helping my growth this is stalling me
this is not the PERT you know like there
does come apart a point where it's
painful to let someone go and it's
almost like you have to work through
that if it's not over abusive and you
don't mean like it's harming you more
than you're there and then there's
almost like this like the opposite is a
lyric in a song
the opposite of love is not hate its its
indifference and if you get to
indifference in your marriage that's
kind of the point where it's like okay
it's time to not a moment of
indifference but like this constant
setting of indifference that like maybe
you're not growing and it's time to like
somewhat split up that to me is a more
healthy split up than like I don't know
like divorce out of anger and hatred
that there's clearly something there
that needs to be worked through until
you either get back to love or to
indifference you know and that's just
what's coming up it's not the truth yeah
well and I think one of the things that
I see and is just because of my
experience a lot of what I see is women
who and this is this is a complete
generalization and it's not universally
true but there's this idea that this
because I discovered it in me I see it a
lot in my comment in conversations that
I have with other women which about
relationships is like you're not making
me happy so and and and and you're not
you know and so I I'm going to pick you
a potty like pick you apart in order to
like make you a better person in order
for me to be happy and there's and and
the this in the United States almost
obsession with I'm an empath married to
a narcissist and and that I need to and
that somehow that you know without the
willingness to look at in inside at how
am I being a narcissist it's I'm going
to point the finger at you and you're
the narcissist and and we've made
divorce so easy that people are not
grappling with the reality things they
are in fact just as narcissistic at if
not more than
the partner they're claiming is abusing
them I was thinking as you would talk
about it just makes stronger cases I was
making before against you know the sort
of the whole not the concept of merit I
could make an equally strong case for
people don't people do give up on it too
easily divorce has become too easy I I
also agree with that weird isn't it how
you can sit very much on both sides of
an argument and agree with both of them
no I you know like Jubilees thing of
like if I'm leaving because I you know
if I'm leaving because I think that you
know because I went through that I was
totally doing the research on narcissist
and luckily I had somebody who was kind
enough to point me to the meme that if
you're pointing a finger at one person
there's three fingers pointing back at
you you know and and you know the thing
you dislike most in others is probably
something you won't acknowledge in
yourself like those are lessons that we
don't really want to acknowledge and it
would be much easier to just get away
from the marriage then too but it but
there but there's this but do you
believe what going back to what you
talked about is like there yeah for some
marriages there you come a point you
know there comes a point at which it's
not that there's something that I have
to work out it's you know it's but like
that's a perfect example of something
where sometimes it just becomes like
evidence of like yeah we can we can part
company in an amicable way and love each
other and then in other cases it's you
know not you know it's I'm trying to get
away from you and like the perfect
example that I the perfect example I can
see is like the the fought the dads who
can like help their kids help their you
know celebrate Mother's Day for for
their kids like because it's like that
if you if you can do that
then I think you're in a place where
it's okay but if you're doing yeah I
don't know I'm not quite following that
thoughtfully that is also actually with
some of my litmus test whether or not
they're but they're a functioning
co-parenting couple is like how they can
function as a family unit even though
they're not effect like a living
together a family unit can you do things
together and some cannot like there's
just there's too much emotion and too
much triggering there and then some are
like when my kids school close down the
end of last year in her school last year
was kind of a co-parenting person's
dream because there were so many
campuses that one person could send them
to school school bus and pick them up in
a different location and scenery when
you switched custody on Wednesdays no
problem but there was both when a couple
would break up the amount of times their
kids were pulled out of this school
because it was an alternative school
right clearly one parent was on board
one parent wasn't on board of the school
but when the school closed the amount of
somewhat friction that happened between
co-parents of light weight now which
school are they going to go to right my
school or your school and like you know
and I mean it's like my life versus your
life rather than what's best for the
school like what's the best school for
the kids right what's the best it's
gonna be the most employment maybe one
goes to one and one goes to the other I
don't know like that this is my point if
that was but like that they it used to
work and then it change and it was like
okay are we in here for the kids or are
we in here for you know I mean for
myself and my my own needs being met
first and is a single parent let me tell
you I also need to make sure my needs
are met right like so it's not that your
needs don't matter if all the sudden you
need to drive your kids three hours to
get to and from school every day that's
a real important need on your family but
ya know my mind just like kind of circle
back to you know what am i ready to let
go of and I think that the the you know
marriage thing is a perfect example of
being willing to let go of an idea of
how something is supposed to be you know
it's like my idea of who you know you're
supposed to be who I'm supposed to be
what what a marriage is supposed
supposed to look like I think ultimately
like in the United States I I firmly
believe that what the United States is
going through is a we're in a
dysfunctional marriage like between the
two political parties like the and we're
having to have this come-to-jesus moment
of like okay so are what are we doing
are we are we splitting up are we stick
together are we willing to are we
willing to stick through this and and
deal with our and I think you know
you know the fact that fifty percent of
marriages ended in divorce
people are don't aren't willing to stick
through and like work through their
stuff together so like of course it
would make sense of like no we're just
gonna we just ignore you and you know
try and pretend you don't exist yeah
letting go of what things are what we
think things are supposed to look like
but that's a scary thing to do because
then you're in this like wait a minute
everything I thought is wrong well you
know you don't do it all at once right I
mean that would be that would be scary I
get that from being a parent like having
becoming a parent having like this
entity that you think you can mold and
shape right and there's a way parenting
is gonna go wait this is gonna go and
all it ever does is fall apart like the
one thing you know is it's never going
according to plan
starting with the birthing or adoption
plan it's never gonna happen and then
welcome to Parenthood and that's from
literally something you could form right
like a child is as much a blank canvas
way more a blank canvas than a partner
when you marry an adulthood who comes
with all of their childhood all their
trauma and he's like the perfect
triggering mechanism partly because
she's a mini but like this whole I had
an expectations of how it would go and
whenever I have that that is when things
fall apart
where is when I can be like what's here
what's present what's beautiful what
works here and it doesn't like there's
no way I'm giving her
later or anything like there's no
divorce for my kid no matter what unless
I die there is no divorce process and
thank God because I would not have been
capable of being in any kind of
relationship like this I might be now
but before she was born before I had
this experience there's no way I would
have been and that's not don't have a
kid and then get married
what was that her there are places where
marriages are like that where there is
literally no at least not for the woman
maybe for the man but not for the woman
you know there are there are plenty of
places where there is there's no you
know the marriages as as much of a total
commitment as the child is but it's
interesting isn't it he's an interesting
point sort of goes as an unquestioned
thing but there is no divorcing yourself
from your children not a choice that's
on the table I mean however difficult it
may be to divorce a spouse it is an
option on the table whereas well I mean
that's you know so it is there it's just
it is this is just a bit what seems a
bit more extreme with children but yeah
you're right it is that and it's not
like that's the weird having a child and
placing them for adoption is one of the
most loving selfless acts I can't
imagine going through pregnancy and not
have you know like there's a lot that
comes up with that and you're not
because your option to give that child
away truly is it conception and
therefore no I don't even know what they
look like what they exist like anything
and so like having the child and and
place it with a family that you think
can better better care for them to me
it's nowhere near the same as like
having a like I think the wound as a
child is different being a seven eight
year old your parents can't take care of
no matter how awesome you are there's no
awesomeness enough to like for them to
get over their addiction for them to get
over the neglect and that parent is your
parent versus you know maybe being
placed for adoption when you're a child
you're gonna have some kind of wounds
possibly but not in the same way as like
like my kid can do absolutely anything
I'm never gonna divorce her she can
murder she can do literally anything I
will visit her in prison
right like she's my I love her no matter
who she is and what she does I can't say
that for any other human being on this
planet as someone who recently kind of
sort of I'm ready to get back but did
disown my sister a year ago I didn't
think that would possible a week two
weeks before it happened but she was
family family's family and how much
family for me had to fall apart in order
for me to actually like find it in other
places and find what it is yeah you know
that being willing to let go of like the
idea of what family looks like what what
anything looks like in you know in life
expectations you're talking about right
just expect at least expectations of
others yeah even if not for yourself at
expectations others yeah okay you not
live up to my expectations one of my
favorite phrases is the you know is
expectations or premeditated resentments
oh that's great I love that I like that
one and but at the same time there is a
bringing in Jordan Peterson I remember
that there was one you know something
that he talked about of like but if we
don't have expectations of other you
know it's like you know there's letting
go of expectations and yet the concept
of a gothic love is the idea that I
can't be coming as well is the I hold a
vision of what is possible for you and
so like there's it's not exactly that
it's not like I have a particular clear
vision of what is possible for you but I
know that you will become more than you
currently are so you love you and I also
love everything that you will be in the
future yeah I'd not looking that you're
in a state in a perpetual state of
growth kind of thing right and but there
I remember Jordan Peterson talking about
you know that that disappointment that
you have or the feeling that comes up
when someone that you love is not being
who
who you know they could be and so it's
like whole you know so it's like letting
go of the expectation but at the same
time holding the vision of like you know
if we don't if we don't have
expectations of each other then you know
they're it's like Manassas we we hold
each other you know it's like we hold
each other up we you know yeah but you
want to do that
hahaha but we want to do that in a
consensual way it's a tricky one isn't
it because any any any goal or
expectation immediately becomes a judge
as well right so it's a really it's a
really yeah it's a well and they're
Hennigan I like I like bringing in the
concept of the consent with it because
like I'm part of I just started being
part of a mastermind birth and I am I
have basically asked them please expect
me to do this because in making that
commitment like I am I'm saying I want
to be held accountable for not not meant
not meeting my expectation to this group
which is a commitment and it's
ultimately a commitment to myself but a
commitment to the group of doing this
thing every day and so but there's but
what happens when you have an
expectation that is a an agreement you
know there's a one sided agreement which
is I think one expectation basically is
yeah right because I'm expecting you to
know what my expectation is and live up
to it without me even necessarily be
able to verbalize it and put it in my
conscious and so when you fail I'm gonna
have all the emotions about like what
that means for you as a person and this
was something that you had talked about
I think in the very beginning Kyra and I
but when I was talking about the
shopping cart and stuff of like what you
get mad at is the person you invented so
like the only thing you have to get bad
out as the person who invented right
some of us at return the shopping cart
so they're inconsiderate and lazy so I'm
mad at them because they're
inconsiderate lazy I'm the one who made
them inconsiderate lazy I don't know
what their
circumstances are right and so then my
level on top of out of me making people
who are making those people lazy and
selfish to that they're wrong right they
how dare they make those people that way
I'm making them wrong for that right he
bookends
it's that self-perpetuating but having
that there some of the consents and the
expectation in that that like we're we
don't have a conversation about our
expectations right that marriage could
be a five-year contract or forever it's
just forever so you fail if it's not
forever you know that when you sit down
and start a team and this is part of
Raymond's
protocol I love that I was just watching
yesterday of like working through this
document of when there's a disagreement
how do you what happens I mean I think
marriage would actually be perfect when
there's a disagreement what do we do do
we go to bed and sleep on it to me don't
even talk about it till it's over
talking about these things beforehand
even if they don't work it's like then
we fix it right well that doesn't work
for you jump on the zoom call we're
having conflict I'm not in the right
space second time I need like that ever
it happens to be to have it written out
and this is what happens when there's
conflict you to continually be able to
say these are my expectations and you
didn't eat them is that on you for me no
no I made you in the in the open
relating polyamory non-monogamy worlds
there's a lot of a lot of conversation
about that bringing the bringing things
to the conscious awareness of like okay
what are our agreements because when
you're in a you know when you're in a
monogamous relationship there's a lot of
things that are just sort of inherent in
that and when you introduce someone else
there are you have to make agreements
about what you know like okay I am this
is what I'm agreeing to this is what I'm
willing to you know and then you have to
have that negotiation and I think that
that's something where a lot of times we
don't make those things explicit of what
are the things that what am I giving you
what am I agree what am i agreeing to
was in the context of this relationship
anthems
you know because I might need to be a
you know it might mean mean I have to
let go of the you know the idea that I'm
going to have you know that I'm gonna
have your your undivided attention at
all times or you know and yeah so I like
that I like that tailor made marriage
contracts right where you actually own
whatever in writing but at least have to
discuss and go what are we actually
entering into here what is our marriage
what is what is our marriage about right
rather than this one-size-fits-all you
know love honor cherish until the day we
die whatever bollocks that you know that
yeah I that that would remove a lot of
my antipathy towards the institution if
it was if it was more like that as he
say he just actually explicitly stated
rather than this whole bunch of its
expectations that come along with the
package whether you asked with the agree
to it or not yeah yeah I really like
that I really yeah and the weirdness of
like no contract is this nebulous
contract like having the monogamy vessel
it's like you have it you have a
different expectation than I do of that
right and we're gonna come into conflict
am I allowed to flirt am I allowed to
dream with other about other people like
I might want to watch porn like what is
the the thing right there's still
conflict but a lot of it swept under the
rug because you're not dealing with all
the couples I know that are probably a
Marez truly polyamorous have had to have
better communication and a deeper
relationship than the monogamous ones I
know because you can't just let that
fester on the surface you have to dig
into it and have to deal with it and you
have to deal with the jealousy even when
it's not you're in the wrong it's like
I'm feeling it so it's right to be
talked about even if it's not putting it
on someone else and I love the idea of
the explicitness and how it's not in a
lot of marriages would fix that and
that's between two people imagine all
the unex
in it whatever the opposite of explicit
is for everything in society like the
shopping cart and this is what I was
talking about was like if we truly
wanted to maximize society so everyone
put their shopping cart back then okay
but we have millions of these tasks all
of which are varying degrees of
importance to various one to other
people right
so it's like well how do I know what
level this is that society hasn't
decided it's all just not explicit at
all you're supposed to follow all of
these rules and all of these unwritten
ones in social interactions again you
know hygiene and health care like
everything and it's like okay which one
do you want me to match yeah because I
can't maximize all of them and so again
if you want me to focus on the shopping
cart I will focus on the shopping cart
but I can't do it all until finding that
one thing that like you okay I can fix
this for you but if everyone want this
one person wants me to fix shopping cart
one person wants me to fix this it's
like no no I need one thing to fix the
one thing to focus on to make better and
then yeah see I had some here as they
say an order slightly strayed from the
actual question that where it seems a
little bit I was straight from that but
I don't think it it it's ultimately like
initially one of the things that we were
talking about is letting go of our ideas
of what something is supposed to be and
so we're talking about how how do you
how do you let go of you know it's like
okay I want to let go of an idea of how
something supposed to be but then how do
you maintain social cohesion when you
let go of the weight of your idea of how
something is supposed to be that's a
tricky balance isn't it as it's tricky
little balance does know it is because
in self-governance part is like not
making things law but getting enough
people to comply that it works because
if it's law right if you make it a law
you have to return your shopping cart
you're gonna be fine you're gonna be
arrested if you don't then that becomes
a higher metric right so my ice cream
melting before I can get it inside
because I don't have enough spoons it's
maybe not as important as a thousand
dollar fine and you know like being
posted on some website so yeah I'll let
my ice cream out and I'll make sure I
get that back that's not the same as
finding out why my shopping cart isn't
put away and helping me figure out you
know I need that maybe I don't have to
go grocery shopping if I don't have the
spoons to shop and put stuff away and
return the grocery cart like finding
that a lot of the tension in society is
these in explicit contracts that we are
haven't consented to in any way and some
of us
even able to consent to because we can't
understand it right like wait what's the
big deal about the shopping cart this
was that a big deal did we care about
that I wasn't even aware like that level
of and the thing that you know a word
that just popped into my head as far as
that the shopping cart thing is you know
one of the things that our current
called our current society has optimized
for is efficiency and so sometimes the
most efficient thing that I can do is to
push my cart like up onto you know so
it's not going to like you know I'll at
least some you know there if I'm not
gonna return the cart I will push it so
to into a place so it's not going to
roll into somebody's car like you know
but I you know because that sometimes is
the most efficient you know way cuz
maybe like it's it's a day where I
couldn't you know I tent I because of
this I've been thinking about like what
do I do
I tend to park near like I try to be
aware of where are the cart stalls so
that I can ear it so I don't have to go
out of my way but if I can't park near
one I will sometimes just push it to
someplace you know close by because more
efficient I was not aware when this
whole thing started that America does
not have a deposit on carts because that
was part of it I was like what about the
deposit like that's very different it's
a different motivation I want to get my
dollar back
versus every time you get a cart they're
connected you put in a quarter a dollar
and it gives you a cart and so you go
and take it back you get your dollar a
quarterback and it's enough of an
incentive that people do it there's the
odd shopping cart in the in the in the
parking lot but very rarely except it
costs over they don't have the deposit
and then they're everywhere but but
staff nicely together right you find a
mate for yours and put it with it and
I'm like then why don't its money
I'm sorry money to put these things on
but like why are you go I don't
understand do they have them in Europe
Eric yeah yeah yeah yeah this yeah you
put a pound coin in and yeah yeah I
other solution people do the right thing
III like my brain is like kind of
short-circuiting at the idea like I got
never an assignment
the idea you don't have it I'm like but
why like I was told in nineteen shopping
and it's weird it's only a pound right
which is nothing you just spent on
exactly it's enough it's money right
it's enough to get people to totaling
back with their cart to get their pound
back if he gonna turn my car because he
wanted the pounds and I was like I like
having interesting yeah like I I'm yeah
I mean that needs to be when I was a kid
all bottles and cans had deposits on
them and kids would spend their weekends
going around the park to get a few quid
it's great I don't get why we stopped
doing these really obvious simple things
that work and there are people we still
do that in terms of the cans and but
there are people who like who do that
professionally now like you know you're
doing that because there are people who
are doing it professionally yeah I mean
here too there's actually almost like a
union like don't collect bottles in
their alleys that aren't yours you will
get in trouble home right yeah no
somewhere as I put my note nicely the
mothers there's Avalon milk bottles that
are a dollar 25 deposit those I don't
put out in the alley except when I'm
extremely late like no those ones I
rinse out and bring back because it's
enough of a barrier right and that's the
question with economics with these
deposits like changing the incentive and
that's like well that's it and then it
breaks the whole the whole litmus test
of are you a good human being because
what you're doing is are you willing to
get your dollar back how important is it
to get your dollar back because there
are days especially if it's a quarter
deposit where because of that I will
leave it by my car and so on you know
now granted like so we have like we're
like at Costco there's what what what
word would I use stalls to to return
your cart to so like you
it's a metal like a metal thing with a
little lip on it you know just push your
card over into it and it'll stay in that
you know you can push it up into into
another one or whatever and then the
Costco employees will come and collect
all those cards because the parking lots
are ginormous and so like do you have a
lot of places to return them or is it or
is there just yeah that's pretty good in
Europe anyway they're pretty good
there's lots of yeah there's lots of
places
yeah lots of stations you again you
won't return it it won't be worth your
dollar record on leaving them in the far
corner you've got anything there was
enough the people will actually do
exactly I have a question because when a
shopping cart thing is my burden I'm
still like in it I close it in game B I
was like how because it is actually
related to this topic about how much are
you ready to like what are you ready to
let go of in our versions of the game B
how much of your version of game B
relies on everybody else feeling being
doing something right that that idea
again my self-governance like just let
everyone do their own thing let's just
actually self govern which is my own
thing but like how much that's my
version right everyone has to be willing
to let go of self government governing
everyone else so they can self-govern
well that's me and eating everyone else
to let go of that like how much because
the more we're willing to oh not and
just explicitly state it I think the
better off we are but we have to know
when we're trying to like right everyone
has to be generous everyone has to be
cooperative everyone has to know that
Trump is a horrible human being and
there's no or needy qualities in him
right like these are the things we're
like if you don't believe that you're an
idiot like it okay me like those kind of
things that are like okay no that's not
self-governance anything that we need
everyone's do because this is the point
is if 95 percent of people put the cards
back who cares about the 5 percent if
we're all the five percent various
places but we're all getting mad at each
other for the 5 percent to do the thing
even you know they mean like because we
haven't we haven't explicitly stated
what's import
and what's not important yeah I mean I
don't know if this necessary applies to
shopping carts but the argument would be
that yeah it's only 5% not doing it but
if it's easier to not do it than to do
it and there's no consequences for not
doing it and people see people doing it
not doing it and getting away with it
then more and more people will start not
doing it is the argument I'm not
necessarily saying it holds up but that
would be the argument well what what I'm
saying like I think it brings it back to
like what are what are our assumed
agreements that we it's like what what
are what are the things that we assume
that everyone else is doing that or that
everyone else thinks the same way and
that's not actually a very easy thing to
find out because it's ton of like a fish
in water it's like well that's just the
way you know like you grow up in a in a
particular environment it's like well
that's just the way people look at
things not realizing that not everyone
looks at things in that same way and my
husband and I have actually been
encountering that one recently because
of some implicit assumptions that we
each have we've been having an ongoing
discussion about the Second Amendment
because he's a strong he has a he's a
strong advocate for the Second Amendment
I'm not strong strongly opposed to it
but I have my things of like I love your
mommy which one the second firearms
right okay but like there's there are
these and you know we're getting down
into some nitty-gritty like views about
how we view each other it's like I have
a particular model about the military
and people in the military in my head
and the fact that I have that model in
my head is kind of horrifying to him and
so like we're trying to where as we're
trying to navigate how do you like you
know there there's an input there's a I
said I keep wanting to use the word
implicit but I don't know if that's the
the right word but there's there's a
there's an agreement you know that he
has that you everyone looks at the
military in this way and if you don't
like that there's a moral like it
triggers a moral response and so like
which you know and like that's the model
I have in my head and I have you know
and I there are other things where you
know he has a model in his head and I'm
like how could you possibly hold that
model in your head mm-hmm
you know it's it's this idea that we're
supposed that that everyone's supposed
to have this particular model and you
don't realize oh wait a minute not
everyone has that concept in their head
and like how do you how do you
understand make an implicit agreement
more explicit now I have to look up the
word implicit sorry the Second Amendment
doesn't apply to the military though
does it I mean the second moment is
about the citizenry having a right to
our military really is it as I
understand it anyway it's about that
it's about retaining the right to
overthrow the government by by bearing
arms right that's that's the spirit of
it as I understand it that's the spirit
of it and my it's not that I'm against
the Second Amendment I just don't
understand it because the Second
Amendment was written when the only
thing that you you know it was written
the the right to bear arms and then
there reached a point at which the
middle you know the the government the
military had no sense of it and so my
the thinking in my head is like at that
point why does it matter and you know
we're yeah I'm getting definitely
getting an education about why you know
you know why for some people it does
matter and trying to like reconcile that
with my views of the world and so but
yeah like how you know and going back to
the marriage thing we have a reason to
not like say well screw you and you know
I'm out of here like there's a commune
there is a commitment between us and so
there's a reason to sort of like on what
you know for me a desire to want to
understand his perspective because there
is a commitment there is a reason to
want to understand you know the
difference between how we think and if
you don't have that like I mean granted
this one's not like well let's just say
he had he had a moment of like oh my god
I don't know if I can be with you and
that happens sometimes you you know you
get caught off guard and big emotions
come to the surface and that that's
there but like because there is that
commitment because there is the amount
of work necessary to like break that
commitment it forces you to like work
through those you know when those things
come up whereas like if there's not a
strong you know if there's not a strong
commitment like I don't know how many
people in my life where it's like we had
a disagreement and then we just never
really talked to each other again
because there wasn't a there wasn't a
motivation to work through the emotional
difficulty that was necessary to see the
other person's perspective I think all
of this stuff is so like important to
game be like because how can you know
it's like we're making those things that
were implicit and just so implicit
implied but not plainly expressed it's
the definition of that and you know it's
like yeah explicitly is implicit we want
implicit become explicit because some of
us don't get implicit we have very
different implicit ideas yeah and so
what was we're at the very ends of our
hours do closing thoughts but one of the
things as it came up for me we were talk
about your husband and you was that like
there's this weird underlining energy of
like you have to be willing to let
something go to keep it like you don't I
mean you're married you're you're tied
together and at the same time being able
to freely say I don't know if I can be
married to you if you feel that way
about guns right like there are some
marriages you can't say that in right
even implying there's a possibility of
divorce as grounds for divorce basically
and then there's other where like listen
I need to be able to say these things I
need to be able to say this is a
deal-breaker even though it's not really
right like I probably not actually get
married I'm divorced over this and at
the same time like I need this to be
processed it's like big emotion and yeah
and whereas pushing it down breaks
everything but it's like the polite
thing to do
I have a better sense of like if he
pulls out the do you know if he if he
pulls out the divorce word I know that
something there's something underlying
that's bigger and she just give him you
know some space and if it's you know if
it's me like if I do it and I don't ever
pull out the divorce word but I'll get
close to it and it no you know fer for
him it's I know okay give him his space
don't push for him it's okay what's
going on let's talk about it let's you
know so it's different for each of us
but you know when he when one of us
pulls out that word you know it's like
after after he did it I was like you
know a couple hours later I said he
pulled out the D word today I was like
yeah we found one of my sacred cows all
right we are out we are running out of
time but I love this conversation and
where it's gone because I do think it
all tied back to the to that question
you know and I guess ultimately it comes
down to am I ready to let go of my
implicit assumptions about yeah am I
ready to go up am I ready to bring to
the surface my implicit assumptions and
be and be willing to let them go if
necessary yeah
I like that the implicit explicit like
just a constant like recommitment to
that like oh we're what is happening
here that is implicit and let's make it
explicit let's make it an actual without
making it law right without making it
listen your arms are cut off if you
don't return the shopping cart that's
what gets people to return the shopping
cart like and this is where the
different change self-governance isn't
then you let shopping carts be all over
the place it's that you look at well why
aren't people returning them and how can
we get them to like a deposit and having
those little those little entryways be
more often and like changing the system
so it works for the more and more people
until you get to the 95% well you've
just hit the answer jubilee you just die
cut people's arms off how many times you
can have to do that before everyone
starts returning their cars once twice
really you know it's a small price to
pay for everyone returning their carts
forever Africa the grand scheme of
things in times when you store we know
we don't steal anymore if you take this
as the total sum you know you would only
do it once or twice right and everyone
would return their carts forever and so
it in the grass it's a teeny weeny weeny
weeny prized couple of people lose their
arm here's the thing right that shopping
cart yes if that was again the one thing
in society that we cared about their
arms cut off if they were square sort of
like let's just forget about it
so my ATD gets my arms cut off that
sound and then that registers and all
the ATD brains that we don't do shopping
carts okay cool but now it's like you
didn't bring wine to dinner your tongues
cut out right like it's like wait what
no just tell me the explicit things
right yeah do you have any closing
statements Erik no and then he really
nicely well and I just wanna I loved the
the point that you made Jubilee as you
know okay what is it what are the things
that we care about and what is
preventing people from
being able to do that and I think that
there is an immediate assumption you
know it there it's so easy to jump to
the conclusion of their lazy their this
their that instead of there's something
that's preventing them from you know
like yeah I love that lesson that they
are just lazy and selfish it could it
could be that right and you put them in
the box you create them you make them
selfish and lazy then you get angrier
than their selfish lazy you punish them
be like yeah but it was like they are
actually just selfish and lazy yeah
that's key that's the truth sure okay
goodbye YouTube